Guide to the Maurepas collection, 1694-1749
Maurepas collection, 1694-1749
- Box Thirteen
  Of special interest: Pellerin's reports on state of Navy funds; an account by the head of the French army in Piedmont of the battle at Cony against Savoy and Sardinia; a memorandum on freshwater fish for Lent; a secret agent's report from Genoa.
- Box Fourteen
  Documents from 1744.
  Reports and memoranda cover: trade with Russia; the Levant; taxation; corsair warfare; Navy archives; Mediterranean operations; expenses; French commerce in general; the armament of ships and its funding; warfare with British; treasurers; the case of La Lievende; commercial regulations for Naples based on report on trade; the Acadtmie Royale de Musique (the singer Lany's dispute).
  Other documents include: orders; a list of ships.
  Of special interest: Maurepas' memorandum on the state of the Navy in 1745; the marquise de Mézières' plan for invasion of England; Fournier's report on losses in French commerce during years of war with England and the consequent need for strong trade; proposal for a new method of fighting enemies at sea.
- Box Fifteen
  Documents from January 19, 1745 - June 1746.
  There are several documents connected to Thomond. Also: the duc d'Enville's observations on a voyage; d'Albert's review of his career. Reports and memoranda cover: English ships; French trade with Spain; corsair warfare; Irish Jacobites; Irish soldiers; the Stuart cause; Scotland; recruitment; expenses of the Navy and of the colonies; replenishing Navy funds; the treaty of Utrecht; the relationship between the comédiens and the Académie Royale de Musique.
  Other documents include: orders; requests for pensions; recommendations.
  Notable documents include: an eye-witness account of the Battle of Freiburg (War of Austrian Succession); an account of the siege of Louisbourg; a 39-page plan for French commercial settlement in Chile; Maurepas' report submitted at Aix-la-Chapelle peace talks on ways of protecting French commercial interests; Maurepas' memorandum on (the second) proposed expedition to aid the Stuart cause; report by Fournier on how to save "le débris du commerce en France"; printed memorandum documenting the case of two French ships disputing corsair booty.
- Box Sixteen
  Documents from September 1746 to c. 1751.
  Documents include: inventories of documents from various departments of the Navy made by Lafillard, the Navy archivist. Reports and memoranda cover: the progress of the Franco-Prussian War; the Corsican situation; the state of the Navy's finances; Spanish commerce; English finances; armaments; the battle of Cape Finisterre; a plan for invading Scotland; the separation agreement of the Prince and Princesse de Talmond.
  Other documents include: lists of officers; a list of ships and their destinations.
  Notable documents include: a book manuscript on principles of navigation with color diagrams.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Jérome Phélypeaux de Pontchartrain Correspondence
1694 - 1708
Box 1, folders 1-55
1708 - 1709
Box 2, folders 1-7
Series II. Incoming and Outgoing Correspondence
1732 - 1741
Box 2, folders 8-44
1741 - 1744
Box 3
1745
Box 4
1745 - 1746
Box 5
1746
Box 6
1746 - 1747
Box 7
Series III. Documents
n.d. - 1732
Box 8
1732 - 1738
Box 9
1739 - 1740
Box 10
1740 - 1741
Box 11
1741 - 1743
Box 12
1743 - 1744
Box 13
1744
Box 14
1745 - 1746
Box 15
1746 - 1751
Box 16
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Jérome Phélypeaux de Pontchartrain Correspondence
  - 1694 - 1708
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] March 21, 1694. Compiège, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] March 25, [1694] Compiègne, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] July 15, [1694] Lesneven, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] July 18, [1694] Morlaix, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] July 19, [1694] Tréguier, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] July 23, [1694] St. Malo, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] July 25, ]1694] St. Malo, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] July 27, [1694] Avranches, 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 2, [1694] Le Havre, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 3, [1694] Caen, 2 ll. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 7, [1694] Valogne, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 11, [1694] Le Havre, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 12, [1694] Le Havre, 2 ll. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 21, 1694. Boulogne, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 27, [1694] Dunkerque, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 LS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] April 21, 1695. Marseilles, 10 ll. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 LS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] April 24, 1695. Marseilles, 6 ll. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 19, 1695. Toulon, 2 ll. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 19, 1695. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 21, 1695. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] July 6, 1695. Aix, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] May 3, [1696] Herbaut, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] May 8, [1696] Richelieu, 6 ll. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] May 17, [1696] Rochefort, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] May 19, [1696] Rochefort, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] May 22, [1696] Rochefort, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] May 26, [1696] Rochefort, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] May 29, [1696] Rochefort, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 2, [1696] Rochefort, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 5, [1696] Rochefort, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 9, [1696] La Rochelle, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 12, [1696] La Rochelle, 2 ll. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 14, [1696] La Rochelle, 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] June 16, [1696] La Rochelle, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] After June 16, [1696] La Rochelle, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] "Vendredy" [1697?] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 ALS to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] August 5, [1699?] Paris, 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] "Mercredy" [before September 1699] Versailles, 2 ll. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] "Dimanche" [after 1699] Marly, 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Chancelier de Pontchartrain] "Dimanche midy" [after June 2, 1701] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Pontchartrain, Elènore Christine de Roye de la Rochefoucault, comtesse de AL to Comte de Pontchartrain [ca. 1707] Paris, 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Pontchartrain, Jérôme Phélypeaux de, 1674-1747 AL to [Comtesse de Pontchartrain] [ca. 1708] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Bigorre, ALS to Cardinal Fleury [n.d., n.p.], 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Du Châtelet, Gabrielle-Emilie Le Tonnelier Breteuil, marquise, 1706-1749 AL to Maurepas [n.d.], 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucault, duc d', 17__ -1746 AL to Maurepas [n.d.] [Toulon], 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Orleans, Jean-Phillippe, Chevalier du, 1702-1748 AL [Draft] to Louis XV [n.d., n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - De Rousel Beaumanoir L to Maurepas [n.d., n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Rozier de Jonquière, AL to Maurepas [n.d.], 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Voltaire, François Marie Arouet de, 1694-1778 AN [Request for further details] [n.d., n.p.], 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Maupeou, René Charles de, 1688-1775 ALS to Maurepas "Mercredy soir" [Paris], 1 l. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Villars, J-A de Varengeville, marèchale de ALS to Maurepas "Jeudy", 2 ll. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Baldini, comte de ALS to [Marville] "La 2nd Jour de Pacques" Bastille, 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Bory, AL [draft] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain [1707-1709] [Callao?], 4 ll. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Chabert, L [draft] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain [April 1708] [La Concepcíon], 3 ll. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - [Chabert] L [draft] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain [September 1708] Concepcíon, 8 ll. [With typescript] (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - 1708 - 1709
    - [Chabert, ] L [copy; draft] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain [September 1708] Concepcíon, 8 ll. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bory, L [copy] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain [ca. 1709] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bory, L [draft] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain [1709] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Bory, L [draft] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain April 1709, Port Louis., 5 ll. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bory et Chabert L [in unknown handwriting] to M. Bruny April 9, 1709. Saint-Louis, 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Bory, L [draft] to Chancelier de Pontchartrain April 24, 1709. Port Louis, 11 ll. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Pontchartrain, Louis Phélypeaux, comte de, 1643-1727 L [draft] to Chabert September 10, 1709. Paris, 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II. Incoming and Outgoing Correspondence
  - 1732 - 1741
    - Ollivier, Blaise-Joseph LS to Maurepas January 6, 1732. Bitche, 5 ll. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - L'Hotellier, LS to Maurepas April 10, 1732. Paris, 1 l. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Ramon, M. de L [copy] to Philbert Orry June 14, 1733 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Ramon, M. de LS to Maurepas June 25, 1733. Paris, 1 l. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Ramon, M. de LS to Maurepas June 26, 1733. Paris, 1 l. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Maillet, Benoit de, 1656-1738 D [Lettre M. de C-----y... pour lui donner une idee générale de ce qui s'étoit passé...] 1734, Marseille., 50 ll. [Draft] (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 LS to the Abbess of Chellus March 13, 1735. Versailles, 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - d'Albert du Chesne, Antoine, chevalier, 1686-1751 ALS to Maurepas March 26, 1735., 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Maillet, Benoit de, L [copy] to M. de Villeneuve July 6, 1735 [Marseille], 4 ll. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - L'Etanduere, Henri-François des Herbiers de & Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 L [copy] to Maurepas August 13, 1739 [n.p.] 2 ll. L [copy, frag.[ to De Brailh January 1, 1735. [n.p.] 2 ll. L [copy, frag.] to L'Etanduere April 14, 1739. [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - L'Etanduere, Henri-François des Herbiers de, ALS to Maurepas December 31, 1739. Rochefort, 4 ll. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Gigou, Noel ALS to LeClerc January 8, 1740. Riez., 12 ll. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - [Gigou, Noel] L [Resumé of Gigou's letter of January 8, 1740 to LeClerc] [January 8, 1740, Riez], 1 l. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Gigou, Noel ALS to Maurepas January 11, 1740. Riez, 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Le Clerc ALS to ? February 12, 1740. Versailles, 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - de la Mothe, Jacques Bigot LS to Maurepas April 24, 1740. Brest, 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Aubenton, Françoise-Ambroise d', LS to Maurepas August 5, 1740. Versailles, 7 ll. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Larnage, Louis de L [copy] to Admiral Vernon August 28, 1740. Santo-Domingo, 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - de la Mothe, Jacques Bigot LS to Maurepas September 17, 1740. Brest, 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 L to d'Antin October 7, 1740., 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Buthaud, ALS to Maurepas October 15, 1740. Paris, 4 ll. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 L to d'Antin October 23, 1740., 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 L to d'Antin [Draft] November 8, 1740., 6 ll. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 L [copy] to Marquis d'Antin November 14, 1740. [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 AL [Draft] to Champigny December 1740, 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Larnage, Louis de, L [copy] to Admiral Vernon December 21, 1740. [Santo Domingo], 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Antin, Antoine-François de Pardaillan de Gondrin, marquis d', 1709-1741 LS to Maurepas December 22, 1740., 4 ll. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Larnage, Louis de, LS to Maurepas December 22, 1740. Saint-Louis, Santo Domingo., 8 ll. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Larnage, Louis de, LS to Maurepas December 23, 1740. Saint-Louis, Santo Domingo., 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Rochalar, comte de ALS to Maurepas December 24, 1740., 4 ll. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Larnage, Louis de, LS to Maurepas January 12, 1741. Santo Domingo, 5 ll. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Duclerq, MS [Journal de tout ce qui s'est passé la Jamaique] March 12, 1741. [n.p.], 32 ll. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Lecomte, Z ALS to Maurepas April 12, 1741. Valencia, 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Fr déric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 L [copy] to La Rochalar April 21, 1741. [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - de la Mothe, ALS to Maurepas Brest, 1 l. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - de la Loe, ALS to Maurepas April 26, [1741] Versailles, 3 ll. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - de la Rochalar, LS to Maurepas April 30, 1741. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 1741 - 1744
    - Luzerne, François de Bricqueville, comte de ALS to Maurepas May 5, 1741. Brest., 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 ALS to Maurepas May 13, 1741. Versailles, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 L to Comte de Watteville May 16, 1741., 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Watteville, comte de ALS to Maurepas May 16, 1741., 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Micault et Cie LS to Maurepas May 17, 1741. Paris, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - d'Arguien, Paul François de la Grange ALS to Maurepas June 19, 1741. Saint Onge, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Mailly-Nesle, Armande de la Porte Mazarin, marquise de ALS to Maurepas September 2, 1741., 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Mailly-Nesle, Armande de la Porte Mazarin, marquise de AL to Maurepas October 1741, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Mailly-Nesle, Armande de la Porte Mazarin, marquise de ALS to Maurepas October 1741., 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Mailly-Nesle, Armande de la Porte Mazarin, marquise de L to Maurepas November 7, 1741., 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Duvernay LS to Maurepas December 6, 1741., 9 ll. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Rozier de Jonquière ALS to Maurepas December 17, 1741., 7 ll. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Gardane, Antoine ALS to Maurepas December 21, 1741. La Ciotat, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Rozier de Jonquière ALS to Salley January 15, 1742., 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - d'Arquien, Paul-François de la Grange ALS to Maurepas February 30, 1742. Rochefort, 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Bontemps LS to Maurepas May 24, 1742., 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Ruffec, Marie J-L Bavyn d'Angervilliers AL to Maurepas August 1742, 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hamendaxie y Casanova, Juan Bauptista de, LS to Maurepas September 22, 1742. Nantes, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Baldini, comte de ALS to Comtesse de Baldini [1743?] "de la Bastille", 4 ll. & frag. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Remy, ALS to Marquis de Châtelet [1743?] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Vierry AL to Maurepas February 26, 1743., 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Boyer d'Eiguilles, Alexandre Jean-Baptiste, marquis de, 1708-1783 ALS to Maurepas March 14, 1743. Berlin, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Guillot ALS to Maurepas March 18, 1743. St. Malo, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Gilly, LS to Maurepas April 25, 1743., 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Baldini, comte de ALS to Maurepas October 22, 1743. Bastille, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Lamotte, ALS to Maurepas October 28, 1743 [Paris], 4 ll. (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Muniain, Juan Gregorio LS to Campo-Florida January 13, 1744. Chambèry, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Court la Bruyère, Claude-Elisée de, 1666-1752 LS to Maurepas January 19, 1744. Toulon, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Daudin, ALS to Maurepas January 29, 1744. Paris, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Campo-Florida, Louis de Reggio, marquis de L to Maurepas January 31, 1744. Marly., 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - O'Bryen, ALS to Maurepas [February 1744] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 AL to Maurepas February 1744, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - O'Bryen, ALS to Maurepas March 5, 1744. Paris, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Laffilard, ALS to Maurepas April 4, 1744. Paris, 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Saint-Simon, Louis de Rouvray, duc de, 1675-1755 ALS to Maurepas April 9, 1744. [?], 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas May 10, 1794. Lyon, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas [June 1744] [Toulon], 4 ll. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Campo-Florida, Louis de Reggio, marquis de, LS to Maurepas June 2, 1744. Flanders, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas June 21, 1744. Toulon, 2 ll. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas June 25, 1744. Toulon, 7 ll. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas July 9, 1744. Toulon, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 ALS to Salley July 14, 1744. Toulon, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Campo-Florida, Louis de Reggio, marquis de, LS to Maurepas July 15, 1744. Bergues, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Thomond, Charles II O'Brien, viscount, Clare earl of, AL to Maurepas July 15, 1744., 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 ALS to Salley July 16, 1744. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 ALS to Salley July 19, 1744. Toulon, 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas August 11, 1744. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Mézières, Elénore-Marie-Thèrèse Oglethorpe, marquise de, AL to Maurepas August 29, 1744 [n.p.], 8 ll. (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Le Clerc, ALS to Maurepas September 4, 1744. Paris, 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Le Clerc ALS to Maurepas September 5, 1744. Paris, 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - De Lage de Cueilly, ALS to Maurepas September 13, 1744. Paris, 4 ll. (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - De Lage de Cueilly, ALS to Salley September 13, 1744. Paris, 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas September 22, 1744. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas September 27, 1744. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__- 1746 AL to Maurepas September 29, 1744. Toulon, 3 ll. (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - 1745
    - La Vallière, Louis-César de la Baume le Blanc, duc de ALS to Maurepas [1745?] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 AL to Maurepas [1745], 3 ll. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Poulain, Jacques ALS to Louis XV [1745] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Poulain, Jacques ALS to Maurepas [1745] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Torres, Roderigo de L [copy; frag.] to Enseñada January 5, 1745 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - de Court-la Bruyère, Claude-Elisée, 166-1752 LS to Maurepas January 6, 1745., 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Enseñada, marquis de la L [copy] to Campo-Florida January 9, 1745 [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - De Court-la Bruyère, Claude Elisée, 1666-1752 LS to Maurepas January 15, 1745. Gournacy, 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Le Clerc, ALS to Maurepas January 23, 1745. Le Havre, 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Saint-Simon, Louis de Rouvray, duc de, 1675-1755 ALS to Maurepas January 25, 1745. [?], 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Salabary de Benneville LS to Louis XV January 26, 1745. Toulon, 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Saint-Simon, Louis de Rouvray ALS to Maurepas February 15, 1745 [?], 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Sisley [?] LS to Maurepas March 20, 1745., 3 ll. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Bonnet, Jean-Baptiste ALS to Maurepas March 31, 1745. Marseilles, 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Saint-Simon, Louis de Rouvray, duc de, 1675-1755 ALS to Maurepas April 4, 1745 [?], 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - De Lage de Cueilly, ALS [copy] to the infant Philip of Spain April 5, 1745. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - De Lage de Cueilly, ALS to Maurepas April 7, 1745. Toulon, 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - De Lage de Cueilly, ALS to Maurepas April 8, 1745. Toulon, 4 ll. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Mailly-Nesle, Armande de la Porte Mazarin, marquise de, AL to Maurepas April 11, 1745., 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Mailly-Nesle, Armande de la Porte Mazarin, marquise de, AL to Salley April 12, 1745., 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Bonnet, Jean-Baptiste ALS to Maurepas April 30, 1745. Marseilles, 3 ll. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Saint-Simon, Louis Rouvray, duc de, 1675-1755 D [Request for the release...] [May 1745] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Saint-Simon, Louis de Rouvray, duc de, 1675-1755 ALS to Maurepas May 16, 1745. Paris, 1 l. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Arnault du Clavier, ALS to Maurepas May 18, 1745. Versaille, 2 ll. (Box 4, Folder 24)